Guide to the Papers of John R. Lamarsh 1943-1981 MC.14
New York University Archives
John R. Lamarsh Papers
1943-1981
New York University Archives
Lamarsh, John R.
MC.14
12 Linear Feet (30 boxes)
John R. Lamarsh was an eminent nuclear physicist and longtime member of the New York University faculty. He received his Bachelor of Science and doctorate degrees from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology. In the early 1960's, he joined the faculty of New York University's College of Engineering as Associate Professor of Nuclear Engineering and was also appointed Director of the Nuclear Engineering Program. Through his career, he was a consultant with several nuclear oriented organizations and advisory commissions. His primary concerns were to ensure the rational realization of nuclear power and control of nuclear weapons proliferation. The papers contain correspondence, professional papers, manuscripts, lecture notes, notebooks, financial records, transcripts, computer print-outs, microfiche, photographs and audio cassettes. The papers reflect Dr. Lamarsh's nuclear energy policies, his involvement as an educator and his activities in various professional societies.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged by topic.
The collection is organized into 10 series:
Missing Title
Correspondence, 1956-1981
Consulting services, 1957-1981
Advisory committees, 1967-1981
Research interests,1957-1981
Academic affiliations, 1945-1980
Professional associations, 1967-1981
Publications, 1956-1981
Speeches, 1960-1981
Personal, 1943-1981
Photographs,clippings and recordings, 1955-1981
Scope and Content Note
The Lamarsh Papers contain correspondence, consultant agreements, contracts, memoranda, papers, reports, working papers, drafts, manuscripts, proposals, abstracts, lecture notes, notes on meetings, minutes, notebooks, financial records, graphs, figures, transcripts of testimony before committees, transcripts of speeches, computer print-outs, microfiche, certificates of membership and honor, resumes, questionnaires, printed material, photographs and audio cassettes.
The Lamarsh Papers are arranged within ten series: Correspondence, Consulting Services, Advisory Committees, Research Interests, Academic Affiliations, Professional Associations, Publications, Speeches, Personal, and Photographs, Clippings and Recordings. In addition, there are subseries within some of the series: Manuscript Reviews falls under Consulting Services; Books, Other Publications and Proposed Publications fall under Publications. The folders are arranged alphabetically and the material contained within the folders are arranged chronologically.
Historical/Biographical Note:
John R. Lamarsh, an eminent nuclear physicist and a longtime member of the New York University faculty, was born in Hartford, Connecticut on March 12th, 1928 and died on July 26th, 1981. He received his Bachelor of Science degree in General Science from the Massachusetts Institute of Technology in 1948 and attained his doctorate in Physics from this same institution in 1952.
Dr. Lamarsh's first academic appointment was as Assistant Professor of Physics at the University of Kentucky from 1953 to 1954. Following a brief appointment at the Brookhaven National Laboratory, he joined the faculty of New York University and served as Assistant Professor of Physics for one academic year. In 1957 he accepted the position of Assistant Professor of Engineering Physics at Cornell University, where he remained until 1962. Upon concluding his term at Cornell, Dr. Lamarsh returned to New York University's College of Engineering as Associate Professor of Nuclear Engineering and was also appointed Director of the Nuclear Engineering Program.
New York University's College of Engineering had offered courses in Nuclear Engineering since 1950. During the 1962-63 academic year the Nuclear Engineering Program was reorganized and the position of Director of the Nuclear Engineering Program was created. Under Dr. Lamarsh's direction the curriculum in Nuclear Science and Engineering was reorganized and expanded. During this same academic year the College of Engineering was renamed the School of Engineering and Science, taking effect in the 1963-1964 academic year. In 1967 the University's Board of Trustees approved a proposal to elevate the Nuclear Engineering Program to full departmental status, effective on September 1st, 1967.Professor Lamarsh, who was instrumental in organizing the department, was appointed its first chairman.
Dr. Lamarsh held the title of Associate Professor of Nuclear Engineering until 1966, when he was promoted to the status of full Professor of Nuclear Engineering; he held both these positions until 1973, when the New York University School of Engineering and Science merged with the Brooklyn Polytechnic Institute to become the Polytechnic Institute of New York. Dr. Lamarsh served as Professor of Nuclear Engineering and headed the Department of Nuclear Engineering from 1973 until his death in 1981. While at the Polytechnic Institute, he maintained his ties with New York University by serving as Adjunct Professor of Environmental Medicine at the New York University Medical Center from 1973 until 1981.
During his tenure at New York University Dr. Lamarsh published Introduction to Nuclear Reactor Theory (1966). This graduate-level textbook was based upon lectures which he gave at Cornell and New York Universities on the topic of nuclear reactor theory. While at the New York Polytechnic Institute, he published his second major work, which was entitled Introduction to Nuclear Engineering (1975). This publication was based upon classroom notes prepared for courses he taught at New York University as well as at the Polytechnic Institute of New York. In addition to these two substantial publications Dr. Lamarsh published several reports, essays and articles during his illustrious career as an educator and renown nuclear physicist.
Aside from his academic duties, Dr. Lamarsh maintained several other professional positions with various federal, state and private organizations. Among these affiliations was the Brookhaven National Laboratory, where he served as Associate Physicist from 1954 to 1956. His consulting activities were numerous; among the agencies he served were: United Aircraft Corporation (1952-1953); Atomic Power Development Associates, Detroit, Michigan (1959-1960); The Gmelin Institute, Larchmont, New York (1957-1960); Picatinny Arsenal, Dover, New Jersey(1966-1972); Township of Lower Alloways Creek, New Jersey (1973-1978); International Nuclear Service Research, Inc. (1976-1978);the Federal Office of Technology Assessment (19761979); the Congressional Research Service of the Library of Congress(1976-1981); the United States General Accounting Office(1977-1981); the National Science Foundation (1979-1981); and the Pennsylvania Power and Light Company (1980-1981).
Furthermore, Dr. Lamarsh served on the Mayor's Technical Advisory Committee on Radiation for the City of New York(1974-1981), the Advisory Committee on Engineering Science at the New Jersey Institute of Technology (1977-1981) and the Visiting Committee in Nuclear Science, Maritime College, State University of New York (1979). Dr. Lamarsh's affiliation with professional agencies and societies in an administrative capacity was also extensive. He served as president of International Nuclear Service Research, Inc. from 1979 to 1981. He was elected chairman of the Education Committee of the American Nuclear Society's New York Metropolitan Section in 1966 and held this title until 1981. From 1975 to 1981 he served on the Executive Committee of the American Nuclear Society's Education Division. Dr. Lamarsh served as chairman of the American Nuclear Society's New York Metropolitan Section from 1977 to 1978 and chairman of the Society's Education Division from 1978 to 1979. Moreover, he was appointed administrative judge of the Federal Nuclear Regulatory Commission, just prior to his untimely death in 1981.
Dr. Lamarsh's research, which dealt primarily with nuclear power development, was considerable. He undertook and produced extensive studies in the following areas: floating nuclear power plants in Korea, breeder reactor technology, nuclear non-proliferation policy, implementation and impact of the Nuclear NonProliferation Act, nuclear proliferation and the implications of educating foreign nationals, alternative fuel cycles and the Three Mile Island accident.
Dr. Lamarsh's firm belief in the advantages of nuclear power was clearly reflected inhis published research as well as in the speeches he addressed to varied audiences. His primary concern was to ensure the rational realization of nuclear power. He was very concerned with keeping issues of reactor safety and the control of nuclear weapons proliferation up-to-date. Moreover, Dr. Lamarsh made a concerted effort to clarify the relevance of nuclear technology in an attempt to benefit policy making decisions.
Access Restrictions
Administrative records and unpublished reports of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation. Access to files spanning multiple years will be opened to researchers based on the date of the most recent materials. Board of Trustees records are closed for 35 years from the date of creation. Materials related to personnel, grievances, job and fellowship searches and applications, and all files that fall under the federal Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) are permanently restricted. Additional restrictions may apply to other materials in this collection. For questions regarding specific restrictions, please contact the University Archives.
Provenance
The John R. Lamarsh Papers (1943-1981), which consist of 12 linear feet of material,were acquired by the New York University Archives in several installments. The collection was donated to the University Archives by Mrs. Barbara Lamarsh, Dr. Lamarsh's widow, on September 22nd, 1982. Subsequent additions were made by her to the collection on November 16th, 1983 and August 22nd, 1984. The bulk of this material falls between the years 1965 and 1981.
Clippings (information artifacts); First drafts.; Notebooks; Diagrams.; Lecture notes.; graphs.; Lower Alloways Creek (N.J.: Township); China |x Foreign relations |y 1976-; New York (N.Y.) -- Politics and government -- 1951-; Nuclear engineering.; Nuclear physics.; Nuclear energy.; Nuclear energy |v Research |x International cooperation.; photoprints.; Minutes (administrative records); Education, Higher -- United States.; Transcripts.; Speeches.; Résumés (personnel records); Reports.; Brookhaven National Laboratory; Borowitz, Sidney, 1918-; Cornell Universtiy; Einstein, Albert, 1879-1955; Edlund, S. A.; Electric Power Research Institute; Eisenbud, Merril; Glasstone, Samuel, 1897-1986; International Nuclear Service Research; International Conference on Nuclear Non-proliferation and Safeguards (1978: New York, N.Y.); Hanʼguk Chŏllyŏk Chusik Hoesa; Cartter, Allan Murray; New York University. School of Engineering and Science; United States. General Accounting Office; United States. Congress. Office of Technology Assessment; U.S. Nuclear Regulatory Commission; U.S. Atomic Energy Commission; Three Mile Island Nuclear Power Plant (Pennsylvania); Sawhill, John C., 1936-; Review Conference of the Treaty on the Non-proliferation of Nuclear Weapons (1980: Geneva, Switzerland); Polytechnic Institute of New York; Pacific Basin Conference; Heald, Henry T. (Henry Townley), 1904-1975; Oliva, L. Jay (Lawrence Jay), 1933-2014; National Science Foundation (U.S.); Library of Congress. Congressional Research Service
- Series I: Correspondence1956-1981
  Scope and Contents note
  This series contains folders of general correspondence from 1956 through 1981 (5 linear inches). It isessentially a compilation of miscellaneous correspondence that was dispersed throughout the collection.
  - General Correspondence I, 1956-1977 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225860 1
  - General Correspondence II, 1978-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Series II: Consulting Services
  A substantial portion of the Lamarsh Papers (3 linear feet) falls under the second series, ConsultingServices. This series consists of material which documents his services as a consultant to variousgovernment and private organizations. Within the series, Dr. Lamarsh's work for InternationalNuclear Service Research, Inc., the Library of Congress Congressional Research Services, theNational Science Foundation and the United States General Accounting Office are particularlywell documented by various studies and reports.* The subseries Manuscript Reviews includesdocumentation of Dr. Lamarsh's role as a manuscript reviewer for such organizations as theAtomic Energy Commission's Division of Technical Information and the Addison-WesleyPublishing Company's Science and Mathematics Division.[*See attached APPENDIX II]
  - General, 1957-1981 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225861 9
  - Brookhaven NationalLaboratory, 1980-1981 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - G.C. Dewey Corporation, 1960-1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Electric Power Research Institute, 1978-1980 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Fusion Energy Corporation, 1981 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Herbert Boyer Company, 1973-1974, 1979 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Institute for ResourcesManagement, 1977-1979 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - International NuclearService Research Inc. Floating Nuclear Power Plants in Korea: General, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Proposal for Phase I, 1975-1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Report on Phase I, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Proposal forPhase II, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Iran: Nuclear PowerProgram, 1977 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Acquisition of a U.S. Energy Firm, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225862 7
  - Advisory Services Contract, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chinese Coal to Korea, sale of, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Korean Atomic Energy, 1976-1980 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Library of Congress, Congressional Research Services: General, 1975-1981 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Breeder Reactor Study, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Breeder Reactor Study: Index, undated (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Breeder Reactor Study: Report, 1978-1979 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Breeder Reactor Study: Update, 1977-1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Canada Deuterium Uranium(CANDU): Report, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Plutonium Production, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - General, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225863 5
  - General, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Lectures, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - UnitedStates/China Nuclear Energy Relations, 1978-1980 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Westinghouse Electric Corporation, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - EuropeanTrip: General, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Indian Uranium, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - International Control of Nuclear Power, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Nuclear Fuels, 1979-1980 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Nuclear Non-Proliferation Policy, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Nuclear Non-Proliferation and Safeguards: International Conference, 1978 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Nuclear Power and Safeguards, 1962, 1974-1978 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - NuclearResearch Studies, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225864 3
  - Plutonium and NuclearReactors: General, 1962, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Phase I, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Phase II, 1976 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Plutonium and Uranium Production in Power Reactors, 1977 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Three Mile Island Accident, 1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Three Mile Island Radiation, 1981 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Lower Alloways Creek (N.J.), Township of: General, 1974-1978 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - New Jersey Legislative Bills, 1976-1977 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Newspaper clippings, ca.1960-1980 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - Nuclear Energy Issues, 1976-1978 (Box 5, Folder 11)
  - Nuclear Power, undated (Box 6, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225865 0
  - Public Service andElectric Gas Company, 1971-1979 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - National ScienceFoundation: General, 1979-1981 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Nuclear EnergyPolicy Issues, 1976-1980 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Kemeny Commission, 1973-1980 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Reactor Siting, 1979 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Reorganization and Restructure, 1978 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Reorganization Plan, 1980 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Travel Expenses, 1980-1981 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Pennsylvania Power andLight Company: General, 1980-1981 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225866 8
  - General Information, 1978-1980 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Susquehanna Nuclear Power Plant, 1979-1980 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Picatinny Arsenal: Radiation Production, 1967-1968 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Weapons Vulnerability Program, 1967 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Saudi Arabia: King Abdulla University, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Stoller Corporation: Nuclear Moratorium, 1975 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Puerto Rico Nuclear Plant, Proposed Saleof, 1979-1981 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - United States General Accounting Office:General, 1976-1977 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Financial Records, 1977-1981 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Nuclear Exports, 1981 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Nuclear Non-Proliferation Act, Implementation and Impact:Assessment of Implementation, undated (Box 8, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225867 6
  - ReferenceMaterial, 1978 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Review and Comments on Report, 1981 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Roundtable meeting, 1980 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Nuclear Non-Proliferation Task Force, 1977-1980 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Nuclear Proliferation Study, Implications of EducatingForeign Nationals: Preliminary Report, 1977-1978 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Report, 1979 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Research Materials, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Working Papers, 1977-1979 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - General, 1967-1980 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225868 4
  - Manuscript Reviews; Atomic EnergyCommission: Division of Technical Information, 1965-1971 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Addison-Wesley Publishing Company: Science and Mathematics Division, 1974-1978 (Box 9, Folder 3)
- Series III: Advisory Committees
  This series documents Dr. Lamarsh's involvement ina variety of such committees, some of which are noteworthy: the Visiting Committee in NuclearScience at the Maritime College, SUNY; the Advisory Committee on Engineering Science at theNew Jersey Institute of Technology; and the Mayor's Technical Advisory Committee onRadiation, New York City which is particularly well documented.
  - Maritime College, State University of NewYork: Visiting Committee in Nuclear Science, 1971-1975 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225869 2
  - New Jersey Institute of Technology: Advisory Committee on Engineering Science, 1967, 1976-1981 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - New YorkCity: Mayor's Technical Advisory Committee on Radiation: General, 1974-1980 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Appeal Board, 1969-1972 (Box 10, Folder 4)
  - Licensing, 1968-1976 (Box 10, Folder 5)
  - Safety Issue, 1976-1977 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - Medical and Educational Uses of Radioactive Materials, 1974-1976 (Box 11, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225870 0
  - Microwave Standards, 1975-1979 (Box 11, Folder 2)
  - Nuclear Development and Radiation Control Programs, 1974 (Box 11, Folder 3)
  - Performance Analysis of the Bureau of RadiationControl, 1976-1977 (Box 11, Folder 4)
  - Radiation Control Aspectsof Radiation Equipment, 1975-1980 (Box 11, Folder 5)
  - Taskforce onDefining Terms, 1975-1976 (Box 11, Folder 6)
  - Transportation ofRadioactive materials, undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
  - Transportation ofRadioactive materials, 1975-1981 (Box 11, Folder 8)
  - NuclearNon-Proliferation Treaty Review Conference: Leadership Consultation, 1980 (Box 11, Folder 9)
  - Pacific Basin Conference: Technical Program Committee, 1979-1980 (Box 11, Folder 10)
- Series IV:Research Interests
  This series contains folders of materials dealing with a variety of subjects: acid rain, cancer, civildefense, coal, cosmic rays, earthquakes, electric automobiles, energy and legislation, fires, fusionpower, hydrogen, magnetism, nuclear generating stations, nuclear NonProliferation policy,nuclear power, the Oklo phenomenon, ozone, radiation monitors, solar energy, thermo nuclearphenomena, transportation of nuclear fuels, transport theory, turbines, wind power and xrays. Insome cases these folders contain a considerable proportion of materials that document thesubjects, but in others the documents are scanty, often containing only a few pieces of printedmaterial. The folders on Thermo Nuclear Phenomena and Transport Theory contain lecture notesand other material that Dr. Lamarsh apparently used for teaching purposes. The contents of someof the other files suggest that perhaps Dr. Lamarsh utilized these documents in his variousresearch projects.
  - Acid Rain, 1979-1980 (Box 12, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225871 8
  - Cancer, 1976-1981 (Box 12, Folder 2)
  - Civil Defense, 1976-1977 (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Coal, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 4)
  - Cosmic Rays, 1969, 1975 (Box 12, Folder 5)
  - Earthquakes, 1970-1974 (Box 12, Folder 6)
  - Electric Automobiles, 1980 (Box 12, Folder 7)
  - Energy and Legislation, 1974-1977 (Box 12, Folder 8)
  - Fires, 1974-1976 (Box 12, Folder 9)
  - FusionPower, 1957- 1974 (Box 12, Folder 10)
  - Fusion Power: HighEnergy Fusion, 1978-1980 (Box 12, Folder 11)
  - Hydrogen Age, 1955-1960 (Box 12, Folder 12)
  - Magnetic Charges and Current, 1940-1948 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225872 6
  - Magnetic Effect, 1952-1959 (Box 13, Folder 2)
  - Magnetic Phenomena, 1947 (Box 13, Folder 3)
  - Magnetism, 1953 (Box 13, Folder 4)
  - Nuclear Generating Stations: General, 1978 (Box 13, Folder 5)
  - Aircraft-Nuclear Facility Interactions, 1973-1974 (Box 13, Folder 6)
  - Operating Procedures, 1976-1978 (Box 13, Folder 7)
  - Safety Issue, 1973-1978 (Box 13, Folder 8)
  - Nuclear Non-Proliferation Policy: General, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 9)
  - Background Material, 1977-1980 (Box 13, Folder 10)
  - Preliminary Work, undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
  - Report, undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Nuclear Power, 1980 (Box 13, Folder 13)
  - Oklo Phenomenon, 1975-1977 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225873 4
  - Ozone, 1975 (Box 14, Folder 2)
  - Radiation Monitors, 1977 (Box 14, Folder 3)
  - Solar Energy, 1970-1980 (Box 14, Folder 4)
  - Thermo Nuclear Phenomena, 1959-1962, 1973 (Box 14, Folder 5)
  - Thermo Nuclear Phenomena: Problems, 1959-1961 (Box 14, Folder 6)
  - Containing Fuels, 1977 (Box 15, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225874 2
  - Transport Theory, 1965-1973 (Box 15, Folder 2)
  - Turbines, 1967-1970 (Box 15, Folder 3)
  - Wind Power, 1977, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 4)
  - X-Rays, 1974, 1980 (Box 15, Folder 5)
- Series V: Academic Affiliations
  This series consists of materials which documentDr. Lamarsh's capacity as an educator. In addition to lecture notes used by Professor Lamarshduring his early teaching career, this series contains material which relates to his involvement inrevising and updating various academic programs at New York University. His keen interest inacquiring an Aerojet-General Nucleonics (AGN-201M) critical nuclear reactor in order toenhance the educational opportunities offered by the Engineering School at New York Universityis also illustrated. Other material in this series reveals Dr. Lamarsh's interest in establishing aNuclear Activation Center at New York University. Moreover, Dr. Lamarsh's concern for therelationship between energy technology and public policy is apparent in his promotion of aCenter for Energy Technology and Public Policy, at New York University as well as at thePolytechnic Institute of New York.
  - General: Lecture Material I, 1945-1946 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    Barcode #: 3 1142 04225875 9
  - General: Lecture Material II, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 2)
  - General: Lecture Material III, 1956 (Box 16, Folder 3)